I think we're we're we're in a new age
where people are trying to form
themselves
and uh they're trying to say this is who
I am and trying to create their their
identity by themselves. And I think what
the Jedi order teaches us and the master
padawan teaches as well as spiritual
direction and religious life is that we
really cannot form ourselves. We need
others to help us in the formation. Of
course, we have a major role in that.
But we do need the mentor. We do need
others to help us, keep us. And I think
even in religious life, that was for
example Dominic's greatest insight. You
know that in order to truly discover
what it means to live the gospel, it
cannot just be you and the Bible. It has
to be the community also that is shaping
you basically discerning the spirit with
the Holy Spirit.
Father Alejandro, thank you for joining
me.
>> Thank you for inviting me, Benjamin. So,
it's a pleasure to be here.
>> Yes. Um, so before we jump in, I'd like
to ask, how did you, uh, first become
interested in Star Wars? Where did this
love start?
>> Well, it started when I was very young.
So, I was in the third grade, uh, 9
years old, uh, back in San Diego,
California. And, uh, that's when Star
Wars came out in 1977. So when it first
came out, it was something very
different from any sci-fi we had at the
time. So at that time, the most classic,
although it was older, was uh Space
Odyssey 2000, 2001, and that was the
classic kind of philosophical
um kind of slowm moving films, but
really deep. But as a child, that really
didn't excite me. Uh but when Star Wars
came out, that was a complete
revolution. It was like something we
have never seen before.
And um I got to see it 30 times.
>> 30 times. So we were just it was almost
like a Disneyland ride. We just got out
and we went back in and saw the next one
and out and in as much as we could. Uh
our grades went down at school. I
remember even the bishop calling a
meeting of the school and the parents
and because all the grades were going
down at the time. So all of us were just
starruck with uh Star Wars. So really it
made a a great impact in my life and I
think uh what really caught my attention
it was a young kid was that I saw the
mythical aspect of it. It was just epic
and so yes there were shootings and you
know starships here and there and the
whole kind of uh cowboy and Indian kind
of show but also I mean we already
detected even back then as a little kid
the epic of and the mythic aspect of it.
So, and I think that's what's remained
all the way to today.
>> And um father, now I'd like, you know,
for our conversation to focus in
particular on the character of Anakin
Skywalker and his kind of emotional and
spiritual journey. Um we're introduced
to him uh on Tatooine. He's a young boy.
Uh Qui-Gon Jinn, who's a Jedi Master
senses, you know, the Force is is is
strong in him. Uh he's then trained by
Obi-Wan Kenobi. Um can you share with us
a little bit what do you think of this
concept of the Force? What do you make
of it? Well, first of all, I think um
yes, so the first the prequels that came
out later and then the original uh
trilogy basically is the life of Anakin
Skywalker. So basically it's his story
and I think u throughout at least those
uh first movies what the force is is
also developed throughout. So I think uh
George Lucas has been very clear and as
we see also in the film as Ben Kenobi
explains to Luke Skywalker in New Hope
what the the force is for them is
basically an energy field that sustains
and unites all living creatures and also
the force can be used as a force for for
good but also for bad. And so I think
that's the original concept of it and
especially George Lucas concept. Um but
it's also an impersonal force. It it's
uh it's an energy field as he explains
it. Um and I think it's closer more to
what uh Zen Buddhism or Taloism would
understand uh kind of the energy of the
world and so on. so less Christian but
as the stories progress and also as new
writers have uh written about it
especially my favorite Dave Fona uh it's
gone deeper and I think that for him
especially the force has changed more to
something that knows something that
guides so it's more of a personal
spiritual so um from coming from a
toistic perspective I will not say is a
is God or it tries to represent God and
also Many people that write on
homalytics and theology and Star Wars
will compare to the Holy Spirit
sometimes, but I think it's more what
Aquinas would call the order of
creation. So according to Thomas, uh, of
course, God creates with order. So with
intelligibility. So it's not chaos that
we have in the creation in the world.
Everything is ordered. Everything's
placed in the moral order created by
himself. And so that I think that's what
is being reflected in the force. And
especially when you consider that even
for Thomas, the way we behave towards uh
God, towards each other, towards
ourselves has an impact. And so if we
behave in a virtuous way, we have a
positive, a balanced way in our
relationships with ourselves, with
others, and with creation. And when we
behave in a vicious way, in a negative
way, then we have a negative impact. So
that kind of connects to what uh George
Lucas and the whole Star Wars series
talks about the balance and the
imbalance of the force that the actions
how how we use the force how we act
within the force has an impact so either
for positive or for for negative and so
I think it's closer to what Thomas would
call this order of creation so this set
of relationships between ourselves God
and creation and that how we act morally
has an impact in that creation in that
order that God says that for better for
worse. So and that where the whole story
of um original sin comes in and personal
sin where basically we distort the order
of God because it becomes a selfish
thing the way of the Sith as opposed to
one that is for the other constructive
of relationships constructive and
supportive of that moral order created
by God. So that would be my my view kind
of from a tomeistic perspective of what
the force would be similar to in a
mythical way. So I wouldn't say it's a
Christian perspective that is presented
in Star Wars but definitely from a
mythic perspective is presented as this
order that exists in creation and then
somehow it becomes imbalanced by our
actions and balanced by our virtuous
actions.
>> And father we are also introduced uh in
the first film to the Jedi order. What
are your thoughts on this nightly order?
Are there any spiritual parallels to
entering a religious order like the
Dominicans?
>> There's many many um things that are
very common in religious life and to the
to the order. There's even one Dominican
in Anchorage, Alaska that somehow can
turn the Dominican habit into a Jedi
habit. So you have to see the videos on
YouTube. Uh so yeah, so there's a lot of
commonalities. I think the main thing
would be the importance of community. Uh
so the Jedi live in communities and uh
then also the Dominicans like ourselves
we live in in community. The question of
formation also is very important in the
Star Wars and in the Jedi order. So is
the masters and the padawans that are
formed into the force. And so also we
ourselves are formed into becoming more
Christlike and coming to know Christ
even more. So it doesn't come from
nowhere. it it's a personal and directed
formation and also the the role of
meditation. So, one of the main
highlights of the more spiritual aspects
of the Jedi order is their um
contemplation and meditation and the
role that plays in their lives, which
tends to be more Zen Buddhism than
Christian. But meditation is part of our
life as we contemplate uh the
scriptures, as we contemplate the
liturgy, um theology, philosophy, it's
also part of that contemplation of of
basically as St. Thomas Aquina said to
contemplate the truth in order then to
give those fruits unto others. So what
is not like the the order and I think
this is very important because a very
interesting distinction is that um in
sen Buddhism but also in in especially
in the Jedi order one and I think this
is what gets Anakin into trouble later
on and that's why I want to mention it
is that they definitely emphasize
detachment.
So um the Jedha is not supposed to have
any kind of attachments any kind of
emotional attachments because that
therefore creates fear that creates uh
distraction from the way of the force.
And so u as we'll see later on um Anakin
Skyworth struggles with this you know
this detachment regarding his mother the
detachment then regarding Padme um and
so that's uh something that we don't see
in religious life. So our Christian
perspective is like we don't preach that
kind of detachment because what we
really value is love. And so the real
question for us as religious is not the
detachment thing but more what do we
love and how we should love it. So that
depends on the circumstances, the
people, the community and so on. But we
emphasize love. So the reaching out
towards the other not separating
ourselves from the other. But the
question is what we should love and what
we shouldn't love and how we should love
it according to the different
characteristics and um closeness to us
and that's the order amoris that uh
Thomas Aquinus speaks of and also St.
Augustine. So it's that order of love
that he talks about which I think in one
sense that is that is not part of the
the Jedi way and that comes up in the uh
in the sequels also where Luke Skywalker
and thinking of rebuilding the order
after the collapse of the order. That's
one of the issues he really struggles
with whether to maintain that kind of
detachment and and uh within the order
and I think he tends to change. No, we
we need to start reaching out to other
people. So that will be a major
difference.
>> And then father with with regards to
detachment, one of the big themes uh
within that formation is the uh
emotional relationship that's developed
between a Padwan and a Jedi master. And
we see this with Qui-Gon and Obi-Wan. We
see that with uh with Obi-Wan and then
Anakin and then Obi-Wan as well and his
development and formation of Luke. Uh
can you speak a little bit on this
dynamic that has a lot of emotional
veilance within the series? Yeah, I mean
I think um like any kind of um uh
mentorship
um the there's a relationship that is
very very intimate and it's a
relationship that's not created by blood
bond or by kind of emotional bond but
it's really a a mentorship and so in
those mentorships we are vulnerable. We
are um in one sense kind of revealing
the dark side as well as the light side
and looking for guidance and then the
master is there to basically guide us to
bring out the best of us and also in the
mentorship hopefully the the mentor the
master knows what is the best of us and
that's what he's trying to bring out. So
it's a very very close relationship and
it's very similar in our Christian
tradition where we have spiritual
direction and so in spiritual direction
also is this uh relationship that is
established between the spiritual master
and the one being guided that is
intimate close uh much sometimes it's
even closer that you would have with
your own family because you talk about
issues that you would necessarily talk
in with the family but here you talk
because you're trying to discern what is
God's call or um boys within this life
circumstances. So I think that is
reflected in in the Jedi order and but
also in the Sith. So we see this
mentorship. So you can be mentored
towards good or you can be mentored
towards evil. And we see that also in
real life. You know that some people
yeah learn evil from other people. They
see other people doing what they're not
supposed to do and that's what they do
because they see this. So it it's a very
important aspect of uh of daily life I
think. Um, and also I think especially
in today's society where a lot of people
feel I think we're we're we're in a new
age where people are trying to form
themselves
and uh they're trying to say this is who
I am and trying to create their their
identity by themselves. And I think what
the Jedi order teaches us and the master
padawan teaches as well as spiritual
direction and religious life is that we
really cannot form ourselves. We need
others to help us in the formation. Of
course, we have a major role in that.
But we do need the mentor. We do need
others to help us, keep us. And I think
even in religious life, that was for
example Dominic's greatest insight. You
know that in order to truly discover
what it means to live the gospel, it
cannot just be you and the Bible. It has
to be the community also that is shaping
you. Uh basically discerning the spirit
with the Holy Spirit. And I think that's
what we see in the in the Jedi order. We
see that in religious life. And I think
that's something that is lacking today.
So I think a lot of people are trying to
search for mentors but um they tend to
kind of look at to themselves and try to
form themselves. And so that has some
good aspects but also a lot of negative
aspects because very easy we can delude
ourselves.
>> And father I'd like now to turn our
attention to Emperor Palpatine. Um so if
we zoom out um during this time there's
the Clone Wars which is a a galaxywide
conflict uh between the Galactic
Republic and the Separatist movement.
And during this period of major uh
battles there's a lot of political
maneuvering uh by at the time Senator
Palpatine uh who secretly is
orchestrating both sides of the of the
war. Um what do you make of Palpatine?
Well, I mean, Palpatine is a great
villain, and I think part of this
because again, he's the mythical
villain, and so like everything in and
especially in the original series, which
is more mythical than the new ones, um,
you know, evil is evil, good is good,
you know, and so Palpatine is the
incarnation of 100% evilness. And so, I
think he's very very uh much close to
the biblical Satan almost. And so he he
incarnates evil incarnate and he like
the devil doesn't use force to do any of
those changes even with chancellor but
even as he becomes emperor he never uses
force it's I think one of his greatest
virtue is patience there's a lot of
patience so he's been working on
creating this empire for years and years
slowly manipulating telling halftruths
uh basically saying what you want to
here. Uh and basically that's what he's
doing through the whole his whole
lifetime to be able to reach ultimate
power and he's been working very slowly
very slowly throughout throughout the
ages which is what we see in the movies
and so b yeah yeah he works basically
like the biblical devil so which he
whispers to us halftruths and basically
tells us what we want to hear to tempt
us into the dark side and so I think he
u the way he's portrayed that's what
you're that's the true evil is uh so
it's not this force that just kind of by
brute force you know forces you into the
dark side but it's more subtle it's more
of the sension of temptation I think and
that's what he presents to both Anakin
and then he presents also to Luke later
on
>> and and father if we can just sit on on
that relationship between Palpatine and
Anakin in particular how do you see him
manipulating Anakin I mean Anakin is a
character who is at the summit of his
Jedi training he's going to be an
incredible you Jedi Master. Um, he has
an incredible relationship with Obi-Wan
who loves him like a almost like a
father son. How how does Palpatine wedge
this divide in there slowly and then,
you know, break it up?
>> Well, I mean, like Satan, Satan always
knows our weaknesses. So, he knows
exactly where to hit us and where how to
tempt us. And so, I mean, Anakin uh is a
very interesting uh character. And so
you have to see the prequels to really
understand everything that's been there
since the very beginning. So in one
sense that he turns to the dark side is
not a big surprise because from very
young age the one of the things that
really motivates him for a lot of things
that he does is unfortunately fear and
so fear of course as Thomas Aquinus
would say is not necessarily a negative
thing. So it's more whether when it gets
detached from reason and is used
correctly. So for example, we are
supposed to be fearful of dangerous
things not to endanger our lives of that
of others. So that's good fear. But also
there's this fear where you just simply
will do the wrong thing in order to
avoid that fear. And so from a very
young age he was afraid of losing his
mom. He was afraid of death. He was
afraid of losing Padawan later on and
paradame and then he was afraid of death
itself. And so this is what kind of
begins to motivate that's why he wanted
to become the strongest most powerful
Jedi there was because he wanted to
somehow
get rid of the sphere or somehow at
least control the sphere. And I think
that's where Palpatine uh and the
emperor see the weakness of Anaquin
Anakin. And so that's where he starts
working on him. And so it says, "Oh, so
you know, have you ever heard the legend
of Pllegus, you know, and so how he, you
know, has the power to basically bring
somebody back from the dead?" And so, so
he reaches exactly where his fears are
and from that he brings them to the dark
side. But the the the conversion or
towards evil basically doesn't start at
that point for Anakin started when he
was already a little boy. All those
traumas that he had uh and that he was
not able to to to let go of those fears
and and instead of trying to control
that basically to you know kind of go
with the force you would say in the Star
Wars universe. Um, and I think that's
how how the emperor gets because he
knows exactly what are the weaknesses of
of um of Anakin and that's how he brings
him to his side.
>> And so, father, when do you think um it
truly goes wrong for Anakin? Is there an
exact moment that we could point to in
the films where the audience can be
like, there it is. That's the moment
where he's turning.
>> Well, I think it is. Yeah. So, like I
said, it's it's all been his whole life.
And so as we see throughout the whole
series, the Clone Wars, etc., he's
beginning to make those choices where
he's reacting a lot of times out of uh
fear and out of pride. Those are the two
basically vices of Anakin and very
strong ones. And so we we see that from
the very beginning. Father, could we
could we say that it could perhaps be
starting with his love for Padme because
that forces a relationship that's based
on lying and deception because that
relationship as a Jedi Knight, he's not,
you know, he's not permitted to be in
this type of relationship with a woman
and then she's pregnant and and there's
that, you know, there's that.
>> Well, I definitely play major. I think
it goes even further back though. I
think it goes with his mom. So I think
when when uh Quing Yong picks him up at
the planet to take him for training and
basically was a slave like his mom and
for some reason he gets freed and of
course there has to be a way the emperor
interveners to free also his mom but his
mom doesn't get freed and so then he has
to separate from his mom who is the only
one he has in life. There's no brothers,
there's no sisters, there's no father.
So this is the only emotional connection
that he has. So I think it begins there.
And so then that gets reflected in his
relationship with Padme because then
with Padme he's afraid of being alone.
That's is one of the his biggest fears
of losing those he loves and being
alone. And so Padame becomes for him
also that kind of uh this is what I'm
going to hold on to to support my
emotional. So I would say it's not
really love that he really loves Pame.
It's more that he finds in her. Okay,
this is something I can use for my
emotional support and that's how so he
doesn't have what we would call
Christian love which is sacrificial love
that he would be love for her and do
whatever he needs to do for her but it's
more what you have to suffer for me. So
you have you have to be there for me.
And I think that's that's also a
reflection from what already was
happening with his relation with his
mom. And um and I think that's why the
prequels are very important about that
relationship with his mom because that
trauma you begin to see there uh of
separation or his fear of separation,
the fear of the one he loves and then
she gets killed. So he also loses her
and he has the dreams about losing her.
Then those dreams repeat again with
Padme that he dreams that she's gonna
die when she gives birth. So basically
it's the same story. It gets repeated
again because is the same fear that's
been driving him through this whole
period.
>> And so father you would you would say
that Anakin does not actually love Padme
in in the Christian sense.
>> Yeah, I agree. So I I think he's
basically using her uh to this is my my
emotional support and so so then he
becomes controlling he becomes jealous
he becomes manipulative even of paradame
because it's it's not true love in that
sense
>> why do you think father that Anakin uh
bows the knee to Palpatine in that
moment where Palpatine kills Mace Wu
>> well I mean and you already asked
originally uh you know one was the
moment that he kind of okay now he's
evil now is so like I said it it was it
was a long process. So you know um it's
not a um is not a a uh cliff fall. It
it's a slipper slope and and that's how
we fall into sin and and even worse
things. It's not an overnight thing. Uh
some spiritual directors will say really
we do not commit uh mortal sins. It's
very rare. It's really more venial sins
that keep accumulate. is the same thing
we keep repeating and we just keep
justifying and falling into it. So I
think by that time when he falls to his
knees before Palpatine basically he's
just confirming
what the path he has already been into
and because he had already been on that
path for quite some time he doesn't go
back to the Jedi because the Jedi
basically uh remind him of what he was
supposed to be but now he he cannot be
or he won't be or he doesn't want to be
and I think that's the main reason um
because he sees in and in in uh St.
Thomas Aquinus will say uh passions evil
passions uh the vice will cloud our mind
and so in one sense we can no longer see
uh the truth and so we're we're so
caught up already on this path and I
think that's what happens to Anakin so
Anakin has closed himself up so this is
the only way I can kind of face my fears
and so on and so this is the only way
and there's no turning back and I think
that just simply confirms when he
promises of allegiance to the emperor.
But that's been going on for a while.
And he's already been separating from
the Jedi. So, he's already he's been uh
kind of uh fighting with the council
that they don't make him a master. He's
also fighting with Obi-Wan. He'll, you
know, this is his best friend, but now
he doesn't really trust them and that
he's holding him back from being all he
can be. So, that's been also growing for
a while. And so, he he's beginning to
lose his connection to the Jedi. And uh
so, yeah, this is just the final
culmination. And how should we
understand concupisence in light of this
example?
>> Concubisence. Well, I mean, again, it's
more the question of of fear and pride.
And so, like you said, and so I I think
that's it's this desire
for security and uh but that at one
point we we don't find security in
controlling things and I think that's
what he does, you know. So for him is
through control then I can get rid of
the fear or somehow control the fear but
that's not the way we we get rid of it.
It's again as St. Thomas Aquinas talks
about the virtue. So we need to canalyze
that fear that energy that emotion
towards the good. So it's not to
suppress it. So again as I said
originally one of the big differences
between our Christian perspective and
that of the the Jedi or Buddhism s
Buddhism is precisely that question of
this attachment you know for us no the
emotions are good the passions are good
but the question is how do we guide them
do we use them for the good or for the
bad so it's not a question of
suppression it's a question of
channelize to the right way and so that
was the answer for him too to use all
this passion for the
But instead he it was just to control so
he wouldn't have that fear.
>> And father in that moment so he bows the
knee to Palpatine and within let's say a
matter of hours he's killing younglings.
I mean that's an extraordinary change.
Um and it's a fall that the only
parallel I can really think of is is
Lucifer's fall. Um where you're the
highest angel to to Satan. Um what do
you make of that immediate and radical
transformation?
>> Well, I mean I think we we said St.
Thomas Aquinas will talk about uh
despair and I think that's what what he
reached at that point. So once we have
despared basically yeah we would do
things that we would never imagine we
could actually do but because at that
time we're in desperation so we lose the
sense of value the sense of balance u
and so we're just reacting we're just
kind of falling and in this case he's
falling into the anger is basically the
the Jedi have betrayed us uh the whole
republic has betrayed us etc and so it's
just this anger that he has inside and
and it's basically just manifesting
itself. So again, uh once we start on
that life of vice, yeah, we get blinded
and and it's a slippery slope and uh
yep, we end up doing things we we
wouldn't even dream we could do, you
know, because we we're so blinded by it
or by the passion. In this case, it
would be anger.
>> And father, could we also make a
parallel with the despair and
hopelessness that Judas felt in his
betrayal?
>> Yeah. So, I mean, I think uh that um
Anakin Skywalker is basically the
Judah's archetype. And so, he is the
love beloved disciple that basically
betrays the the Jedi and the light side
of the Force um because of fear and
because of pride. And so, definitely
does what he does. The difference of
course between Judas and and Anakin is
that at the end Anakin is able to and we
see this on the the first trilogy uh
opens himself again to mercy with his
son Luke and so when he's you know here
I'm here he says yes you have saved me
already. So that was the difference uh
Judas falls into despair and then he
kills himself. So the logical
consequence
that it's just the slippery slope to
despair and more despair to the end of
life. Uh and but Leia Luke uh have
always seen no there's still good in
him. So there was still a little spark
there that could have been turned and I
think that's why we see in return of the
Jedi Luke really working on that little
flame that was there because I know
there's something there and so that and
that's what saves him at the end which I
think for Judas's car that was gone. So
he just at the despair I cannot be
saved. I will never be forgiven which I
think you see Anakin also when Luke when
first sees Vader uh in um in Endor and
they have that conversation you know
it's over here you know I I know there's
still good in you I think Anakin still
there blah blah he says that name has no
meaning for me I said so I think it's
just like Judas there's no forgiveness
for me this is the path I have chosen
there's no out you know but then he
himself recognizes towards the end and
that makes the whole difference so that
brings the redemption of Anakin
Skywalker uh that thank goodness Luke
had seen constantly there and and worked
on that.
>> And father before before I turn to uh
order 66 which I want to touch on, you
mentioned Luke working on on his father
Anakin and that finding the redemptive
quality and that being kind of the
center part of his kind of journey as a
Jedi or and his formation.
Is there something different in Anakin's
attempt for Jedi glory if if you will in
the sense of wanting to save Padme that
those two loves those two guiding lights
are different in nature?
>> Mhm. Oh yeah. I mean I think well I mean
Anakin and Luke are very similar and I
think um it couldn't it could have gone
the same for Luke and we see that when
he is with training with Yoda and Deoba
and he goes into the cave and so
basically he confronts himself and what
he sees is Vader and when he defeats
Vader and the mask falls off is his own
face. So basically was saying yes this
is part of your heritage you could end
up here you know in this whole thing uh
becoming evil too a Sith lord so but I
think that's also where we see because
it's both the story of Anakin Skywalker
and the story of Luke Skywalker and uh
in the story of Luke Skywalker and
Anakin what we see is their choices and
that's what makes because I think also
Luke is fearful also and I think he's
also looking for uh companionship ship a
place of belonging. Uh he didn't belong
in Tatooine. He was looking for
something else. And uh so he's has the
same fears in one sense as as Anakin. I
think Luke doesn't have the pride of
Anakin. And I think that already makes
him kind of different. But ultimately
it's the choices. So uh whereas Anakin
to confront his fear and confront his
and support his pride uh chooses
basically control and that's his whole
thing. He chooses to control and to
become the most powerful Jedi to control
all this and that's how it's going to
death is going to be kept away and fear
whereas Luke I think is more open to
redemption is more open to see okay
where can this lead how can uh we move
forward from this and and and basically
reach become a real master Jedi and I
think that's where where Yoda plays a
major role in basically helping him
understand yeah Uh wars don't make a
warrior great. He tells him because he's
expecting also Yoda to be this great
warrior and then he sees this little
green guy. Uh so but that's because he's
trying to this is not what the Jedi life
is all about. You know it's precisely
this whole question of choosing the
good, choosing the light. Um it's not
about moving rocks and all that. It it's
really a path, you know. And so I think
Luke learns that quickly. And of course
you see also him rebelling against that.
he leaves uh Yoda and goes to save his
friends although Yoda says he won't be
able to help them and actually yeah he's
not able to help them um so we see also
him struggling with that but ultimately
he is making the right choice and I
think also when he is his father and um
in front of the emperor and so on where
he says you know here I am in
defenseless strike me down so it's kind
of like the uh would I kill baby Hitler
had I known that he's going to be Hitler
should you know I have the chance here
baby Hitler should I kill him or not and
that's what he's confronted with you
know but he has already learned the way
of the force by that time and says no I
I will not do it and he won't fight his
father he will not fight because that's
not the way of the jud because that
leads to anger and then anger leads to
everything else that Anakin Skywalker
did choose and that made the whole
difference for the two of them
>> and father can I posit a theory also on
the differences in choices that Anakin
and Luke make and and with regards to
Luke Luke not having the pride of
Anakin. I wonder if Anakin did not have
the benefit of those 30 years of the
silent hidden life that you know our
lord had as well um growing up 30 years
where he was just quietly living his
life and Anakin um from the get-go when
he has a public life when he's
discovered by Qui-Gon and the Jedi is is
told again and again and again you are
the chosen one and he makes
extraordinary progress and has an
extraordinary training and and youth and
development in that sense. Uh Luke from
the very beginning has no his humble
existence has no recognition on any
level until he meets Obi-Wan. And I
wonder if that those years of of of
silence were the difference.
>> Yeah. I mean yeah I think you you got on
something very interesting there which I
even think about but uh yeah very true.
So I mean I think um first of all like
you said um Anakin is already being
groomed to be the chosen one. So, I
mean, you're almost kind of grooming him
for pride because you you are the chosen
one. I uh Quang tells him, "I never seen
someone with such a strength in the
force as a little kid that doesn't know
anything about it." Uh, so he's kind of
already set up to be a champion
basically. And so, he's being trained
for that. Um, so I think also what he
lacked was mentorship because I think
uh, Ben Kenobi, Obi-Wan, I think first
of all, I think Ben Kenobi is the
incarnation of the what the Jedi are
really supposed to be because Guan Yong
is a rebel. He's always fighting the
system and he that's why he's not in the
council. Even Ben Kenobi says you would
be in the council if you wouldn't be
fighting them all the time. And even
says you will you will not fight them
anymore. Right? regarding the training
of Anakin and said I have to do what I
have to do. So he's always been the
rebel and he's also teaching that to
Anakin but before when he dies or he's
dying he makes uh Ben Kenobi uh Obi-Wan
promise that he will train the child. So
that's what he takes him on although he
hasn't finished his own training and and
so he's also kind of doubtful. And so I
think I've read somewhere that basically
Anakin really needed a father figure. He
needed a Yoda really. And Ben is more of
a brother. He's your older brother, but
more of a brother relationship. So, in
one sense, it's not that uh Obi-Wan
failed in the formation of Anakin, but
that Anakin really needed more of a
father figure than a brother figure. And
I think so that was also a lack. Whereas
Luke, as you said already from the
Riviera, first of all, he was not he
never had these expectations. uh he was
just looking more for adventure and so
on. He was kind of the young the kid
brother, you know, your younger brother
in the family. Uh and then of course
Obi-Wan knows he's the family. So it's
more because he's part of the Skywalker
family that he says he probably does
have the fort. We need to train him. Uh
but and Ben is older by that time also.
So he has had a lot of experience. He's
seen what happened before. So even the
mentorship of uh of Obi-Wan is a more
mature one. But then he has the the
years with um with Yoda and I think also
that here's the father figure and so he
really guides them like also Jesus going
into to the desert. So he has that more
direct confrontation as opposed to kind
of more discernment I think and I think
Anakin really didn't get that
discernment time. It was more yeah
you're the chosen one so you better
prepare for this and d and I think Luke
is more okay. So because they're also
fearful that he will turn into dark
side. So both Yoda and ghost uh Obi-Wan
are cautious you know it's like okay but
okay we seeing this that so they are
also training him in a way so that he
won't fall.
>> So I think yeah so that that makes a big
difference.
>> And then father no I'd like to turn our
attention to to that fall and to go back
to Palpatine executing order 66. Uh this
is a a unique moment in the in the
prequel trilogy where uh clone troopers
now turn on their Jedi generals. Um
Anakin, who is now Darth Vader, um is
hunting down the last remaining Jedi.
This is an extraordinary moment. What
what what are your thoughts on order 66?
>> Well, I mean again, it was something
that uh the Emperor had planned a long
time ago. So I mean for him from the
very beginning, he knew that the biggest
obstacle to assuming full power were the
Jedi. So that was the the biggest
obstacle. And so he'd been planning for
this at one point where he had the
chance to get rid of the the Jedi. And
so that's what he does with Order 66. So
that was no surprise. And so it's
already cuz we already know it was not
an order he just gave right there and
then. But even in the building of the
clones, it was already implanted in in
in their brains that they when he said
that they would react this way and turn
on the Jedi. So it was planned way
before. Um so but I think uh basically
we just see the culmination
that once we kind of go on the dark side
it just keeps growing and growing and
growing and so it's like virtue. So we
have vice and virtue and so if we we
practice virtue we live the good life
that goodness keeps growing we become
better people you know and the same
thing with sin if we fall into vice and
so we become worse people to the point
that it becomes a world thing order 66
you know that even gets rid of people
that were our friends who were our
allies who were the ones defending us
and so we now can see them enemies
because they're no longer we're blinded
basically by by
fear and by that pride and by that
search for power as it was that of the
emperor
>> and father in that moment we have one
Jedi who turns and becomes Darth Vader
and reres you know emotional spiritual
havoc in his own personal life that then
manifests itself in the actions he's
taken against his brother Jedi but in
that same time in that one man's fall we
have what seems to be the fall of the
galaxy chaos in the galaxy now with this
order are there any parallels can we can
you speak to how one person's action can
actually be reflected and magnified
throughout the cosmos in that sense.
>> Well, I mean also we are talking with
very unique people here because uh both
um Anakin uh I mean was considered a
great warrior and so he was a great
master already by that point as we see
in the clone wars very close to the
troopers. Um and so when uh high
spiritual figure falls
yeah it has a major consequence
throughout you know so it's even today
when we hear of you know scandals in the
church and and you know preachers that
fall from grace and so on I mean it
really has a constant it's it's not just
a personal fall it really makes a lot of
people it's scandal so basically a lot
of people lose faith a lot of people
going uh start doubting things. So it
really has a ripple effect in a greater
way than if it's just some kind of you
know somebody who was more obscure and
so on that falls into this. So I think
that's what we're seeing there. And so
uh we see Anakin, we see supposedly the
chancellor who is looking out for the
galaxy and so on who turn basically
um and again
in a very well Palpatine in a very
manipulative. So you want peace, you
know, now we'll have the first Galactic
Empire and now we will have peace
because this is what you always wanted.
So he knows how to, you know, talk to
us. Uh but but it's because they are
such high figures that that's why they
have that ripple and I think that's why
you feel it galaxywide.
Um but at the same time as we continue
the story you know it is one little farm
boy you know that ultimately brings down
the empire ultimately converts the
biggest villain who at the time is uh
Darth Vader back to good you know as
just a simple farm boy who believed who
believe in the goodness of the other and
and of his father uh and who believe on
the on the light side of of the force
and so his actions do make difference.
So I think in in the spiritual life in
in Christian life is the same way. So
any action for good or for bad has
consequences throughout you know when
people ask me many times you know well
why do I have to go to confession you
know because I could confess to God
directly you know I do that every day.
So at the end of the day, we Dominicans
too, you know, we have a refle um kind
of um examination of conscience during
complant and so you think about the day
where you failed and where you uh were
closer to God and ask for forgiveness
and so on. So yeah, we can do that
everybody. Why do I have to go to
confession and I think one of one of the
answers is that because no matter how
hidden whatever we do for good or for
evil has consequences throughout the
galaxy we want to call it. Uh so when we
go to confession, yeah, we're basically
confessing to God. We're confessing to
the church. We're confessing to each
other, to another human being because
everything we do either personal, even
if it's very intimate, it has
consequences throughout. And so that
gives us also great power because we can
change the world one step at a time. and
and and you know even today when we see
a lot of aggression, a lot of conflict
and so just to smile in the street makes
a big difference because you brought a
little bit of joy to somebody in a world
full of darkness you know you want to so
it does make a difference so any little
action you know it's the story of the
the widow also that puts a little coin
you know just small a penny basically in
the co but that may because that was all
her life that she puts in there and so a
little action does have consequence,
major consequence.
>> And father, speaking of the consequences
of Anakin's actions, uh the climax of uh
episode 3 is of course that iconic
battle of Mustafar between Obi-Wan
Kenobi and Anakin Skywalker. Can you
speak a little bit on that on that um
conflict and that moment that takes
place in the volcano planet of Mustafar?
>> Yeah, sure. I mean I mean we see the
consequences of of uh what Anakin has
chosen and so basically he has created
uh hell for himself and that's why their
Mustafar is like hell and so he has
become part of that and of course
Obi-Wan still loves him you know he
tells him you know I loved you and like
a brother and so on and so but by that
time what we see basically is the
consequence of sin and so basically he
has closed himself in Um, one of the
things that I think is very different
from the kind of Star Wars mythology,
but depends who you ask, but with
especially with sen Buddhism and talism
is that it's not a yin-yang thing. So,
in the yin-yang tradition, basically you
have the evil and good that needs to be
bal that's the balance, you know, and so
that somehow we have to keep the two. In
Christianity for Thomas for example the
evilness is is the negation is
nothingness you know so the good is is
everything is the good and and evilness
is simply nothingness and so it's not a
balanced thing is basically the the
corruption of the goodness and I think
George Lucas also sees that although he
tends to be more on the yin-yang but
he's also say because even when they
talk about the what Anakin is supposed
to be doing which he does at the end
which is kill the emperor
kill the the force of evil in in the
galactic empire uh is to to basically
destroy evil. So it was not a balance of
well we have the emperor and myself
living together. No, it was the
destruction of evil. So ultimately he
has to have Christian perspective at the
end of it. So I think that's what we're
seeing in this battle between Ben Kenobi
and and Luke and so and Anakin. So
Anakin has already uh chosen the evil
side and he's so blinded that simply
cannot accept love. Um, I don't remember
the movie right now stars Robin Williams
and I think it's May dreams come or
something like that.
>> Yeah, May dreams come true.
>> May something like that. I thought that
was the best depiction of hell. So his
wife commits suicide and she ends up in
hell. And of course the whole story is
that the character of Robert Williams is
trying to bring her out of hell. And uh
and hell is not shown as a fiery place
and as we always usually think of hell
but it's basically like an upside down
cathedral and she is just dark and she's
there kind of like this you know like in
a trauma position fetus position and so
on just completely locked up in herself
and heaven is right there. So all she
needs to do is just simply stand up and
walk into heaven. But she's so caught up
into herself, so closed in that she
cannot do that, you know, and so Robin
of course tries to do that and finally,
thank goodness, he brings her back. But
I think that's what you see in in
Mustafa. So I mean, Anakin is completely
closed already in his anger, in his
pride. Uh he also thought he killed a
parad at that time and so he's just
closed out. He cannot open himself to
the love of of of Ben and the redemption
that he's offering him right there and
then. this is your chance to redeem
yourself, you know, don't do this. Uh,
but he's just full of anger and full of
pride and and and blinds him to to to
the real. So, he's he's close to is the
consequence of all his choices
basically. And that and that's what
we're seeing fighting right there. One
more chance that he could okay put his
weapon down and join Ben Kenobi and come
out and save and then he would realize
Pam was fine, you know. Uh, but no, he
chose him. So, that's why it reminds me
also of this other movie because Yeah.
that basically in hell uh somebody was
saying uh God continues to love us
because God is love. He doesn't hate us
even in hell but it's weak who cannot
respond to that. we're so close in and
in one sense that's the suffering in
hell that somebody's still trying to
love us although we don't want that you
know we don't want that love and I think
that's part of the suffering of hell you
know we see a little bit that on Dantes
to Divine comedy uh and I think that's
what we're seeing there with Anakin
Skywalker
>> and father could you speak a little bit
about the different understandings in
violence between the Jedi and the Sith
because there's that moment where Anakin
is is left um burning he's both arms are
have been cut off by Obi-Wan. And
Obi-Wan looks at him and has the
opportunity to to kill Anakin. And
Anakin, of course, as Darth Vader will
uh contribute and create a lot of
suffering for everyone, but he does not
kill him. And we've seen in in certain
depictions in different movies and in
the stories, the Sith have a very
different approach to violence.
>> Yeah. I mean, definitely. I think uh
well first of all like I always think um
Obi-Wan Kenobi is the incarnation
almost dogmatic of what the Jedi is
supposed to be even more than the other
characters. Uh even Yoda I would say
Yoda is the wise master. Yoda is a wise
master but but uh Ben Obi-Wan is the
rule guy. You know he he's he's sticking
to that tradition no matter what. And I
think precisely at that moment he's
being a true uh a true Jedi. So he will
never use violence uh to destroy. So
that the the Jedi have always used are
supposed to use uh violence for defense.
It's the last resource. It's uh the only
for defense is only to seek peace. And
that's why they would use u weapons like
the lightsaber. So they would never do
it for attack. And so basically there is
he has accomplished what he was supposed
to do bring justice. So he basically
stops Anakin you know but then he leaves
the judgment to the force
you know and so we in Christian life
will say the same thing you know so we
are called to stop evil but then we
leave the ultimate judgment to God
himself where who are we to judge you
know we don't know the heart of the
people and so I think that so he did
what he was as a true Jedi he did so he
just simply stopped Anakin right there
and then he couldn't do anything more
else then it was up to the force that he
whether he survived or not survived he
did survive becomes even more evil
becomes Darth Vader but then he also has
a spark of salvation and gets redeemed
at the end so had uh Ben Kenobi killed
him right there and then he would have
died unredeemed you know it would have
been the same fate of Judas's scariot
but um in any case he didn't know what
the future was going to hold for him but
he said this is not my job so this is
left left it to the judgment of the
force. And that's what we are called as
Christians. So ultimately we're not who
am I to judge. Only God can judge. And
so we we are called to stop. Um with
regards to violence, well, yeah, I mean,
I think uh in the Clone Wars is where it
gets a little bit we don't know exactly
where this is going because they are
supposed to be the guardians of peace
and the guardians of justice throughout
the galaxy. And here in the Clone Wars,
we see them as generals. They are the
generals of the troops, the storm
troopers of the um republic troopers and
uh so it's like a different role but
again we can see they're defending
they're defending and that's what the
role is there for defense. uh and we
have within the Christian tradition of
course the just war theory and so on
which is the ultimate um you know this
is the last thing we can do and it's
only for to to stop to defend and and to
search for peace and justice whereas the
Jedi use it for aggression so it's
basically they use the force the
violence to uh to accomplish their power
and so they're using for conquest to
control to to expand their power and so
it's a very different and that would not
be a a Christian way so at all. And so
yeah, I know that some people had
criticized that the but I I just read an
article which was very very interesting
which I didn't even really see it until
I read the article. it was Luke
Skywalker.
And so he has to learn the same lesson
that basically when he confront when he
sees Yoda for the first time in Degoa
and he's expecting this great warrior
and he says wars do not make a man great
because that's not the point you know
the point is peace and and balance and
so on and everything that Yoda
incarnates there in teaches Luke and
Luke eventually learns and so when he
has to confront his father uh he he he
refuses to use force because if he gets
attacked then he defends himself but
basically no I'm not going to fight you
he says because this is not the way of
the Jedi you know also when he has the
opportunity to kill Palpatine he will
not do it because this is not the way of
the so he has learned that pacifism
basically is the way of the Jedi and in
the new trilogy which I mean I still
have to reanal an analyze again because
I'm not too sure but anyway this article
was talking about so when Ray calls him
to come back to fight the resistance and
he will not do it is because he has said
this is the violence is not the way
that's not the way of the Jedi you know
and so and she expects it to come back
so he will be a warrior and that's her
vision of of the Jedi and so where
they're talking to each other whatever
it's like yeah you you don't understand
what the Jedi are we we're not that's
not what we are you know so it's it's to
bring balance to the forces so it's more
of a pacifist um outlook And I think
Luke incarnates there. There's other
things that happened there in the last
movie, but basically that's what the
article was saying. And yeah, I kind of
agree. And so and I think that's why
also um Obi-Wan did not kill. So it was
it was um he only performed justice and
would not take revenge and so on. And so
and he said then left the judgment to
the force. And father, when you look at
this, you know, ultimately long arc to
redemption, um, even if what appears to
be the story of Anakin is is quite sad
and and and very dark, what takeaways
can we can we can we take from this? Um,
what can we learn from Anakin's journey
versus Luke's, for example?
>> Well, I mean, I think Yeah. So, I think
that's what we need to do almost see the
two of them. You have to see Anakin, you
have to see Luke. Uh because again both
so the whole art shows uh none of us are
perfect. So we all have virtues and we
all have vices. Nobody's perfect. But
it's how you live your life, how you are
making your decisions, you know, towards
the light or towards the darkness, you
know, to the dark side of the force or
to the light side of the force. And that
makes a difference, you know. Um the
difference I think of course between the
the the the
Star Wars universe is that a lot of them
for them is a lot of uh it's me through
will and training and so on that I do
the good or I do the bad and as
Christians we know that ultimately we
depend upon God. So it's God ultimately
that's helping us but we need to be
cooperative with that to collaborate
with the force basically and so to be
open to that. Um and so that I think
that's a difference there. But basically
what but both Christianity and the Star
Wars series choices are important and
and and what choices do we make and yes
and from where do we make those choices
because we all have fears we all have
pride etc. But how do we choose do we
channel those for the good or basically
we try to control that try to repress it
and and then that brings us to
destruction and I think that's what both
Anakin and Luke show. So um Anakin
basically keeps choosing to control it
to have the power etc. And so the dark
side and so then that leads to the
ultimate him becoming Darth Vader
somebody who completely different
whereas Luke is always you know here and
there but he's always choosing the good
he's going forward forward and we see
that till the end to the point then that
he can save his own father so it's not
just a question of saving himself
because he also saw that in the cave in
Deoba he could have done otherwise so he
also has to kind of redeems himself or
be redeemed but at the same time now he
has re reached a certain level where he
can redeem somebody else and he's
redeems his father and so that's the the
final teaching of both Star Wars
>> father this has been a fascinating
conversation do do you have any final
thoughts you'd like to share
>> well I mean I I think it's u I mean I
stories like Star Wars and any kind of
mythical stories I think uh yeah they're
not the Christian gospel but I think
they do deal with topics uh that the
whole world deals with, you know, the
question of of vice and virtue, of good
and evil, light and darkness, making
choices, uh, redemption.
Um, I think that's what this great
epics, not only Star Wars, but other
epics, uh, that we have in culture and
so on, uh, teaches us. And they're
important to study them and to look at
them and then compare them to the gospel
epic that we have and, uh, how that also
enlightens us. And I think the main
takeaway both from Star Wars and
Christianity is that nobody can fall so
deep into the dark side that ultimately
cannot be bought to the light side. So
there's nobody that can fall so much
into vice versa that cannot be redeemed
at the end. And I think that's both the
new hope
>> that is so important. Uh father, this
has been wonderful. Um I hope we can do
it again soon.
>> Thank you. Asparagus.